I thought that I would get a fair trial
and that's why I went as long as I did
without taking a plea because I really
believed that once I got in front of a
jury they were going to see how
ridiculous this was and I was going to
be acquitted but what ended up happening
and forgive me if I've told these
stories before but I think they're
important uh what the government did
with me and what they will almost
certainly do with Julian is to invoke
something called sipa the classified
information protection act that changes
everything related to this trial so what
happens is that all of the attorneys on
both sides will have to be granted
temporary security clearances and
literally everything every scrap of
information that comes up in the case is
considered to be classified a classified
document uh Julian would not even be
allowed to meet with his attorneys in
their offices all meetings would have to
be either in the Justice Department
secure conference room which is where I
had to meet my attorneys every time or
uh they would build a temporary secure
area called a skiff inside the
courthouse and they would bring Julian
out of the holding cell provided that
he's not granted bail and he would meet
his attorneys in the courthouse it's
very very difficult and it's especially
difficult because you're not allowed to
take notes on any of these documents
they're classified and so you can't you
can't jot something down your lawyers
can't jot something down to jog their
memories nothing you walk in they check
you you don't have anything that you're
carrying in with you and then when you
come out they check you again and make
sure you don't have anything you're
coming out with that was one problem
another problem is that there's
something called a section six
conversation I had never heard of this
ever in my life until it was invoked in
my case I had asked for 70 documents to
be Declassified so that I could defend
myself and that's what I needed I needed
documents with these 70 documents I was
confident that I would be acquitted and
so we made 70 SE motions for judge
brinka to um review each one and we
would hope declassify
them so we blocked off two days for
these hearings and we went into the
courtroom and the judge said um I'm
gonna make this easy for
everybody and I'm going to deny all 70
of these motions and my lawyers jumped
up objection your
honor said my lead attorney said it'll
be impossible for us to defend him if we
don't have access to any of these
documents these documents prove that
this was a vindictive and selective
prosecution which was one of our
contentions the prosecutor jumped up and
said your honor section six conversation
I had never heard of that as soon as
those words came out of his mouth my
lawyers objected
again and their objection was overruled
and I said to one of the lawyers what's
happening he said just a minute this is
really important and then he said your
honor at least let Council into the
chambers you can leave the defendant out
let us come into Chambers and she said
motion denied so what it meant was that
the prosecutors all six of them got to
go into the judge's Chambers God knows
what they told her in there because my
lawyers weren't allowed in and then they
came out and she said I am denying all
70 of these ions and then that was it
she hit her gavel and it was the end of
it we start walking out of the courtroom
and I said to my lead attorney what just
happened in there and he said uh we just
lost the case that's what happened I
said so now what do we do he said now we
talk about a
plea I told him I didn't do anything
wrong I'm not taking a plea and he
turned and he said you know what your
problem is you think this is about
Justice and it's not about Justice it's
about mitigating damage and I took a
plea a week later that's what I fear is
going to happen to Julian it's not about
Justice it's about mitigating damage
because once they decide they're gonna
get you they're gonna get you unless
you're fortunate enough to be held up in
an embassy someplace you know as bad as
things are in the Ecuadorian Embassy in
London they're not as bad as they are in
adx Mar
or adx
Florence you know so I I fear not that
Julian is going to be found guilty I
think in a fair trial he would clearly
be found not guilty he's a
journalist but it won't be a fair trial
the fix is in especially in this
District the eastern district of
Virginia I'll add one more thing I hired
OJ simpsons's jury consultant he
happened to be the uncle of my best
friend's wife and so he did it pro bono
he flew up to Washington from Dallas we
got him a security clearance and he went
through thousands and thousands of pages
of classified documents finally when he
finished we met all the attorneys I had
11 attorneys plus this guy we met to
discuss strategy and he said listen take
the deal if we were in any other
District in America I would tell you
let's go for it we're going to win this
thing but the eastern district of
Virginia you don't have a prayer your
jury is going to be made up of people
who are from or who have relatives with
the CIA the FBI the defense department
Homeland Security or intelligence
Community contractors you don't stand a
chance and so that's finally what made
me take the deal again that's EX ly what
I fear is going to happen with
Julian you didn't you didn't stand a
chance also because they wouldn't let
your lawyers into the court into the
judge's Chambers to look no and they
could have told her anything uh in in
that meeting they could have said that
yeah that I had you know child
pornography on my computer or I beat my
wife or I I have a Russian passport and
I'm G to flee the country God knows what
they said to her back there but she came
out and she said nothing doing no
defense I want to ask you a bring but
before that I just want to tell our
audience that when you talked about
mitigating damage in your case was the
revelation of the truth that the United
States was participating the CIA in in
particular in torture correct so that
got out and they wanted mitigate that
damage in Julian's case they'd want to
somehow mitigate the damage that they
suffered from their own actions that
were revealed in uh absolutely vetted
and correct and true documents that were
were leaked two week leaks and then
published these are their crimes that
Julian exposed right yeah exactly
they're going to flip it around like
they did with you was their crime of
torture which is against us and
international law that you exposed and
then rather than the country rallying
around to prosecute the officials in
favor of that we've got one of them and
responsible for it we've got one of them
running the CIA right now Gina hospital
and you were prosecuted just like
Chelsea Manning who revealed video
evidence of war crimes
pretty much fasy evidence of a war crime
he's the one who went to jail and was in
solitary and pretty much suffered
torture himself I wanted to ask you
about before Brink him one one question
about uh the skiff that you uh I was
talking to Tom Drake he told me that
they built indeed built one of those
skips at the Baltimore courtroom Federal
courthous in Baltimore where he was
tried or was about to be tried is your a
feeling if it was inside the courtroom
or the justice department and you
probably have no proof of this that your
attorney client privilege would be
violated that they'd somehow be
listening in oh absolutely absolutely I
I assumed from the very first day that
uh that they were tracking everything we
were we were discussing they were
looking at exactly what cables we were
we were uh reading or what we were
printing uh or or even that they were
going through our files when uh when we
finally left for the day I just assumed
that they had access to everything
another not very discouraging fact now
brinka would most likely in your opinion
be the judge if there were a trial of
Julian San correct yes it would be
brinka over the course of many years she
has reserved all national security cases
for
herself one thing
about brinka really really loves to see
her name in print it's not just National
Security cases see in in most federal
district courts uh you're assigned a
case just based on whoever's uh turn it
is right they're just assigned one after
the other after the other in the eastern
district of Virginia the judges pick and
choose what cases they want to hear and
then the cases that really nobody wants
and they're usually minor cases are
generally given to the um the more
Junior federal judges I forget the name
um but brinka takes all the all the
National Security cases she had mine she
had Jeffree Sterling's she had Zacharias
mousawi she has Ed Snowden and now we
know thanks to this mistake that justice
department made that they have that she
has Julian as well well she also has
another high-profile case or had one
that was high-profile until very
recently a woman bought a a painting at
a yard sale for $5 and it looked very
much like a Monae like an original Monae
and as it turned out it was an original
Monae and it had been stolen from the
the Walker Art Museum in Baltimore in
the 1950s and it was in somebody's house
for a half a century they died
and uh it ended up in this yard sale and
it sold for five bucks well the museum
wanted their painting back and this
woman said no I bought this painting for
five bucks and it's going in my living
room and the museum sued her judge
brinka assigned the case to herself
because there was so much media interest
in this long lost Masterpiece from Monae
that she knew she'd be in the post every
day and she was she was in the post
every day that this trial went on and
then the museum got there painting back
but that's what she does you know
she she
very
discreetly Mak sure that she stays in
the news and what better case to keep
her in the news every single day than
Julian
Assange yeah I want to add one more
thing about brinka um she has this she
has this kind of uh kind of a tick uh
it's something that she repeats over and
over and over again with every defendant
uh when she hands down sentence and it
doesn't matter if it's a day or if it's
a hundred years she says that it's fair
and appropriate and if you sit in her
courtroom you'll hear her repeat it in
every single case fair and appropriate
well on the day of my sentencing I was
the last person to be sentenced so I sat
there for hours waiting to be sentenced
everybody in front of me had a federal
drug case uh one of them was this major
trafficker from Thailand and most of
them were just guys who were smoking
weed at the eima or whatever um and then
there were a couple who were
undocumented now if you got caught
smoking weed at the eima she gave you a
year and a day if you were an
undocumented immigrant you were going to
get three to five years followed by
deportation well she would hand out
these what I consider to be Draconian
drug
sentences and children are crying and
clinging at their fathers and the wives
are crying and she's splitting up these
families right there in front of you and
as they're wailing in court she just
leans forward and she says that sentence
is fair and
appropriate well there's there's nothing
fair or appropriate about destroying
families deliberately destroying
families uh because a guy was smoking a
joint you're gonna you're G to make it
so he doesn't see his children for the
next 20 years you're going to deport him
to a country that he doesn't even know
anymore but that's what brinka does
she's uh she's a hanging
judge what was her fair and appropriate
sentence in York John well that's a good
question uh in in my case she deemed 10
years to be fair and appropriate but my
attorneys had negotiated something
called an 11 c1c plea which meant that
it was written in stone and it had been
agreed to with the prosecutors and that
was for for two and a half years 30
months so in the sentence or in the
sentencing phase in the hearing she said
that she had been a judge since 1986 she
had been a prosecutor before that and
she had never had an 11 c1c plea and she
looked at me and she said into the
microphone I don't like it I don't like
it one bit and if I could I would
sentence you to 10 years in prison
but she couldn't so she accepted the two
and a half and I counted my
blessings did you just serve the entire
two and a
half yeah I I got I got no halfway house
time off at all not one hour of halfway
house time I did the whole stretch and
it was because I um I wrote a Blog from
prison called letters from Loretto it
became my second book and uh I continued
to exposed waste Fraud and Abuse at the
prison and in the Bureau of Prisons it
enraged them they tried repeatedly to
throw me into solitary I told them go
ahead I said I've been nose toose with
Al-Qaeda with Hezbollah with the
Iranians and I'm supposed to be afraid
of your solitary in Loretto Pennsylvania
please I said give me a little bit of
credit and they would back off they
always backed off and then one time um
one of the guards mentioned to a friend
friend of mine that the reason that they
kept threatening me and then not doing
anything was that I had access to the
media and they were afraid that if they
sent me to solitary that CNN would be
waiting for them in the parking lot and
they just wouldn't be able to
answer so it saved that's interesting
that leads you to that leads you to the
next question I want to ask
you how did uh your revelation of
torture when the Tria went on obviously
that had to be front and center so uh
whether you were convicted or not the
public got to hear I would think if the
Press covered the trial fairly that
America was torturing now uh since you
serve time we don't hear about that
that's not in the public conscious that
just F fades in to the normal life that
we live just the way surveillance and
all of snowden's Revelations were maybe
a shock when they came out for a while
but now it's just part of the fabric of
our lives in the US that we're being
surveilled uh illegally uh what lasting
effect uh if any did your revelation of
America torturing have and how much do
you blame the media if there hasn't been
any oh I I do blame the media the
mainstream media anyway
uh you know my Revelations LED and and
these are not my words these are John
McCain's words my Revelations led to the
McCain Feinstein Amendment uh
which says that it bans torture it
doesn't actually ban torture what it
does is it it makes um it makes all
national security
interrogations uh fall under the uh Army
Field Manual okay and the Army Field
Manual is very clear about what you're
allowed to do in an interrogation and
what you're not allowed to do but that's
an executive document and so if you want
to bring back a torture program and do
it legally all you have to do is change
the Army Field Manual and any president
can do that with a stroke of a pen you
don't need any congressional action so I
think that my don't say that John Trump
may be listen yeah
yeah he may not know he could do that
you're right right so you know at least
we we haven't had a torture program
since I went public that that made it
worthwhile but you're right Joe the the
public doesn't really care when Gina
haspel was named CIA director uh The
Washington Post called me and they asked
me if I would write an oped uh in
opposition to the nomination did it
gladly and they gave me 1,200 words on
the front page of the Sunday opinion
section major Soap Box uh it led to a
half a dozen death threats uh it was a
big mess but I got my side of the story
out and then even Rand Paul called me
and asked me to go up to his office the
next day which I did to strategize on
how to defeat this
nomination uh the democ rats went soft
at the end the likes of of Mark Warner
and Joe Mansion they went soft and Gina
haspel became CIA
director uh but the story just went away
it just went away quietly and now what
pains me the most is if you look at
public opinion polls a clear majority of
Americans uh support a torture program
after all these years after all these
Revelations after exposure of of these
monstrous things that being done to
human beings a majority of Americans
supports a torture program that's the
most disappointing thing to me and I and
I do blame the mainstream media for that
because they could have jumped on this
issue and they did
not Le U one thing you said was that
this uh law that came out of your case
banned Against torture it's was already
banned yeah by the convention Against
torture that's right you notal treaty
signed by Senate uh ratified by the
Senate which automatically becomes US
law so what did they ban they ban
something they it's like Banning murder
again I don't get Yes again forgive me
if I sound like a broken record but uh
not only are we signatories to the to
the United Nations convention Against
torture we were actually the the
drafters the authors of that convention
besides that we have a federal law in
this country called the federal
anti-torture Act of
1946 and it specifically B and those
things that we were doing to prisoners
at Guantanamo and Abu gra in
1946 we executed Japanese soldiers who
had waterboarded American PS We that was
a death penalty charge to waterboard
somebody in January 1968 The Washington
Post ran a front page photograph of an
American Soldier waterboarding a North
Vietnamese prisoner the day that that
picture ran Robert mcamera who was
Secretary of Defense at the time ordered
an investigation that Soldier was
arrested he was charged with torture
convicted and sentenced to 20 years at
lenworth well the law never changed over
all those years
never so I always contended that it made
no sense for something to be a crime in
1946 and a crime in
1968 and then perfectly legal in
2002 and made no sense it was it was a
bastardization without any changes any
legislation overturning it of course
correct you said there is there's no
torture program now well do you need a
program to torture people no is there
freelance torturing freelance torturing
going on yeah there's a lot of freelance
torturing I mean we we have no idea
really what our soldiers are doing on
any given day in Afghanistan or in Syria
or in Yemen or Somalia or any of the
other 100 plus countries where they
happen to be we have no idea you know we
we get information out in drips and
drabs like this uh soldier in
Afghanistan who was questioning an
Al-Qaeda suspect or Taliban suspect
really is what he was and then as he was
taking him back out of the base to take
him back to his village saw a one of the
sources who was from the same Village
and rather than expose The Source our
soldier took his guy out and shot him in
the head and buried him in a shallow
grave and is shocked he's shocked he's
been charged with murder well that kind
of thing happens all the time we just
never hear about it so I I would call
that in part a torture program John what
do you think is worse from from the
government's point of VI us government's
point of view your revelation of torture
or the revelations of WikiLeaks and how
would Assange be treated by that judge
and depending on your answer I I don't
think that
either one of them were bad I I think
Julian's Revelations were more
embarrassing and that's really the
question here we know now with with
hindsight that literally nothing that
Julian
revealed led to any kind of a long-term
problem for the United States it didn't
expose sources and methods it didn't
expose excuse me it didn't expose uh the
names of confidential
informants it it it didn't jeopardize
relationships it exposed
crimes uh and there's actually a law in
this country saying that it's illegal to
classify a program that is a crime you
can't legally classify something just to
keep yourself from being embarrassed by
it and Julian embarrassed them so I
think that his case is more important
for the government than mine was I would
also say that I agree with uh Garland in
that they don't want Julian to mount a
defense they're going to want him to uh
to take a plea and to keep his mouth
shut because God knows the damage that
Julian could cause them in court you
know my my attorneys early on in my case
raised uh something called the issue of
gry male not black male but it's kind of
gray and what that meant is or was in my
case look I was at the C for 15 years
half of that was in counterterrorism
operations which is the ugliest
bloodiest part of CIA operations
horrible things happen in
counterterrorism you see horrible things
war crimes crimes against humanity human
rights violations and you keep your
mouth shut because it's wartime things
like that happen you convince yourself
to keep your mouth shut well it's the
same thing with Julian God knows what
Julian knows from all the different
documents that he's seen the the
government can't be confident that
Wikileaks has released literally
everything and they're G to be afraid
that Julian's gonna get up on the stand
to defend himself and he's going to
reveal more classified information now
that's going to force the government to
the negotiating table because the last
thing they want is Julian on the stand
testifying on his own
behalf probably won't happen you said
that after uh there's no official
torture program in part because of your
Revelations but so in other words there
are no black sites perhaps although it
could still be going on yeah yeah right
I think that's you had some impact yes
you had some impact though in the end
you served two and a half years in
prison unjustly but you did in the end
do something that may have been worth it
for you uh because there's at least been
uh an ending of official Geor go Kan
told the New York Times in um 2015 that
it was only because of my Revelations
that that the McCain Feinstein Amendment
uh passed and indeed it took eight years
after my Revelations for McCain
Feinstein to pass but he said that that
had I not said anything um the American
people would not have known that we were
torturing prisoners so that that made it
all worthwhile you know John McCain was
wrong on 99% of his policies but on
torture he was he was completely right
well for obvious reasons because he if
he hadn't experienced it himself maybe
he wouldn't have been that's right now
uh Trump on the campaign Trail and in
debates in the primaries Anyway said
that he wanted to bring back worse than
water watering he said water boarding
hell of a lot
worse hell of a lot worse now the guy's
a big BS artist we know that he's always
exaggerating everything everything's
great everything's big
everything's going to be worse uh but
still you say that he has not brought
back an official torture program even
with M hpel at the helm in Langley this
is quite
extraordinary we don't really know do we
we don't know um she was questioned at
length on this issue in her nomination
hearing her confirmation hearing before
the Senate uh intelligence committee uh
publicly and I I would assume privately
as well and um she actually made a
reference to my Revelations saying that
in the
end she realized and the organization
realized that the program was probably
not legal that's as that's as good of an
admission as we're going to get from
bloody G hasel but um yeah but she she
told lawmakers uh in including
Republicans that there would be no
torture program on her watch that that
was a A Dark Day for the agenc see that
the program was conceived and
implemented in the in the ugly days post
911 and that it wasn't coming back now
we're gonna have to take her word for it
I suppose and rely on the media to uh to
make sure that she is telling the truth
and continues to tell the truth but
officially as it stands now there are no
black sites uh anywhere but you know
what Joe that's not to
say you don't really need a black site
in order to torture somebody
what you do is a an extraordinary
rendition now a rendition is if I if I'm
in Pakistan and you're an Egyptian and I
catch you in Pakistan I send you back to
Egypt because you're Egyptian that's
that's an extraordinary Rend I mean
that's a rendition an extraordinary
rendition is if I'm in Pakistan you're
an Egyptian I catch you and I send you
to Israel for interrogation or Syria or
Li
and I say to those intelligence guys
don't torture him right and you wink
don't torture him but uh whatever he
says send us a memo and let us know give
us the transcript that's an
extraordinary rendition those are
illegal but the CIA has never come out
to say we don't do extraordinary
Renditions they've never said that they
don't do them uh while your Revelations
had had some effect positive as McCain
has said and others as you've laid out
here what about the revelations of
Julian Assange the of the we of
WikiLeaks of the war crimes committed
has that had would that have had any
impact on the US no longer committing
war crimes I don't see it myself what do
you
think no I don't think so either I as
terrible as that sounds I mean what
Julian exposed being a being a video
in my opinion was so much more impactful
than what I
exposed uh because you could see it and
then you could keep going back to it on
on YouTube that you're watching a war
crime unfold before your eyes that
should have led to statutory changes it
should have have led to to uh Military
Officers going to prison it should have
led to people being reduced in rank it
should have led to policy changes and
none of those things happened none of
them the government through the media
was able to turn the debate to make the
debate about Wikileaks and not about the
war crimes that Wikileaks uh uh
exposed and one could argue that war
crimes are worse than torture even of a
higher order and it's had no impact and
another thing that we should have seen
was editorials in the New York Times on
the Washington Post insisting that those
people responsible the pilots their
superiors whoever was responsible be
prosecuted and charged at the US never
do this again and instead they've turned
around and also made it about now
Assange personally to smear him when
they once profited from his work
including in those days because it made
the Bush Administration look bad this is
my view uh now that he's made the
Democrats Hillary in particular look bad
he's he's got to be attacked and SM weed
and lost in all this or the war crimes
that were revealed it is just accepted
now there's been no change or any impact
at least in your case there's been at
least an official disbanding of an
official program of torture whether it
carries on or not in in the revelations
of weeks and there was so many films and
documents but the premier one is this
video you're talking about I would think
you'd have to say that shows in Action a
primas evidence of War crime there's
been no impact at all and the media has
turned against this guy yes which is
just unbelievable to me shocking
shocking and disappointing I agree I
have a question on that for for John and
that is um what do you you're mentioning
the the way in which you know torture
and and that was exposed in previous
decades was prosecuted what do you think
has has changed the culture around that
to the point where now there is no
prosecution about it and and in fact
you're you were the one that was
prosecuted for revealing it is there any
specific reason that you can think of or
multiple yeah oh yeah it it was 911 911
was so traumatic inside the CIA it was
such a colossal intelligence failure
every CIA
officer in that building felt at the
time that he had the blood of 2,000
Americans on his hands um you know
you're paid to do one thing and that's
protect the country and you fail utterly
and completely and then at the same time
just after 911 Osama Bin Laden released
a statement saying that that Al-Qaeda
was planning an attack that would dwarf
911 and we had to believe him so um so
people went completely overboard in just
ignoring the law the rule of law human
rights civil liberties they just did
away with them I naively believed at the
time that it was a pendulum and the
Pendulum would swing back in the proper
direction back toward a respect for
human rights and civil liberties and
that just never happened what happened
instead was organiza organizations like
the CIA the NSA the FBI at all um saw
this new found Authority and said oh
this is better than we've ever had it
we're never giving this up and so they
began doing or CIA and NSA began doing
what Jay Edgar Hoover had perfected in
the 30s 40s and 50s and that is going to
Congress every year and scaring the
out of members of Congress about threats
against the country and then demanding
ridiculous increases in budgets and then
getting it I remember going up to kofer
Black one day kofer became Ambassador
kofer black but he was the director of
the cia's counterterrorism
center and this was about uh three four
months after 911 and I I caught him in
the hall and I said kofer I just need
one minute I have an idea for an
operation that I want to do and he put
up his hands and he said whatever it is
just do it I have so much money I can't
possibly spend it
all and so I did it there was no
oversight there was no board that I had
to argue before there was no chain of
command that I needed to get permissions
from I just did it I booked myself a
business class ticket and I went and did
it just like that and the CIA likes it
when nobody's looking over their
shoulders that's incredible what it was
he did not want to know what it was you
told him what you were gonna do no no no
he didn't even know what he didn't care
but it was you know was it to capture
Arabs go go do it another thing too uh
do you remember the movie The Kingdom
with Jamie Fox and a couple of other big
stars well there's a scene there are two
scenes in that that movie one is where
an FBI agent is going to go to Saudi
Arabia to investigate a terrorist attack
that killed his best friend and as he's
leaving um the best friend's Widow
Whispers into his ear kill them
all and at the end of the film where
he's found the Mastermind of the attack
he shoots this guy and the guy's
granddaughter kneels down and she's
crying oh ABA you're shot you're dying
and he tells her my daughter grow up and
kill them
all and when I was leaving for Pakistan
to head counter terrorism uh operations
there as I was leaving the guys in my
Branch were shaking my hand you know
godspeed good luck be careful and my
boss leaned forward and he said kill
them
all and I remember thinking my God is
this what we've come to and it it it was
that's what we had come
to
wow that's uh quite interesting I hope
that doesn't classified stuff you're
telling us here
John it's all in book number one it's
not classified they told you to that
they told you to kill them all is not a
classified uh
order you you're allowed to go and do
whatever you want um Tom Dr Drake told
me a story you reminded me of Tom Drake
of course being The Whistleblower from
the NSA who first revealed the wireless
wire tapping in the Baltimore Sun they
almost put him in jail but he stuck to
his guns and the government knew they
didn't have a case and they dropped it
in the end he told told me that right
after a couple of days after
911 that his Superior that he was
working with she was number three in the
agen in the agency in the NSA went
around talked to the Troops you know the
low level grunts working the
surveillance and to try to keep the
spirits up after 911 and uh they were
quite upset as Drake was that they'd
failed the country they took their job
seriously about providing Security
National Security to the American people
and they were upset that they'd failed
that they had not discovered this 911
plot before it happened and she
apparently said according to Tom uh
would this was the best thing that ever
ever could happen to the agency you know
how much money we're going to get oh
yeah absolutely and they were shock
absolutely that story tells you a little
bit about uh in these agencies FBI NSA
probably at CIA there are lower level
people who who actually believe what
they're supposed to be doing and want to
do the job to protect the US and
inevitably a lot higher level folks
don't see it that way and have been
known to quash investigations if they're
getting too close to tful interest or
whatever and just like Sabel Edmond's
story if you know is that she her
investigation that she had started uh
was stopped by the FBI and I talked to I
worked on that talked to an FBI agent at
his home outside Denver and he more or
less confirmed that that was true that
they were shocked that they were told to
stand out so was that the same with the
CIA as well were they idealistic agents
or is it more corrupt in the FBI than
the
NSA I found the corruption like Tom like
Tom Drake did I found the corruption to
come from the the management levels at
the CIA and not not the lower management
I mean I was I was a branch chief uh
what three times it wasn't at my level
but it was above that at the um at the
level of division Chief or office
director or the deputy directors uh of
the CIA it was all politics for them
they weighed everything W uh against how
it would play at the White House and how
would it play on Capitol Hill and then
at the deputy director level up at the
top they've kind of sort of worried
about whether or not it was legal or if
we could argue successfully that it was
legal even if it was clearly illegal you
know there are so many ways to twist
words and phrases and and say that up is
down and night is day and if they think
that they can pull that off they go for
it but yeah I I my experience at the
agency was very very similar to Tom's
experience at
NSA yeah well that's what I expected so
to sum up what we were saying uh while
you're whistleblowing did lead to some
concrete um changes uh you don't think
that Wikileaks or do you think Wikileaks
Revelations of war crimes and other um
malians by the US government will lead
to any kind of changes it will just be
accepted and continue as normal yeah I
think that's the unfortunate case and I
think it's because
Julian has been portrayed in the
mainstream media even by the recipients
of his
Revelations um as as a
criminal it's crazy the way it happened
it's crazy he's a Russian mole he was a
a a republican um asset that was used to
uh deny Hillary Clinton the presidency
you hear all kinds of stupid crazy
scenarios but uh yeah the mainstream
media I think has forsaken him and
because of that we won't see uh
substantive changes no and and they want
to make sure that nobody else ever tries
that
again they're also as Elizabeth has been
saying they've been using him to promote
and further this Russia gate story
absolutely yeah and I think that it's
interesting it's not just the media it's
also entities that um describe
themselves as U media like unbiased
Arbiters of of bias like media bias fact
check these organizations will label
Wikileaks as known associates of of the
Kremlin and Putin they'll label them as
providing inaccurate or mixed accuracy
in their information but then they'll at
the same time label the Atlantic Council
totally unbiased and totally reliable so
I think that there is definitely e an
effort to smear Julian Assange not just
in the media but in across all sorts of
different organizations so that the
public doesn't trust what Wikileaks
published for sure well that's the
essence of it then right to question
theity of the of any new Revelations
that come out definely that's that's uh
disturbing that executive order by the
way that John referred to is
13526 and it was signed by Barack Obama
which says that the government no nobody
in Government Can classify a document if
it covers up a crime that's being
committed or even
embarrassment So based on that order jul
son should be able to walk out of the
embassy tomorrow because all he's done
is reveal crimes and embarrassment and
um that's not a crime then under Obama's
executive order because uh it wasn't
shouldn't have been classified to begin
with so if it wasn't classified he's not
revealed classified information
[Music]